Guide to the A. P. Watt & Son Records Relating to Rudyard Kipling
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. P. Watt and Son records relating to Rudyard Kipling
1889-1945
GEN MSS 893
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.25
(5 boxes)
The records include writings, correspondence and printed materials by or relating to Rudyard Kipling. Writings consist of holograph manuscripts, corrected typescripts, and corrected proofs. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters from Rudyard Kipling to A. P. Watt and Alec Watt written between 1889 and 1936 concerning both the publication of Kipling's writings and personal matters. Pamphlets by Kipling comprise the bulk of the printed material, which also includes clippings, ephemera and various other items.
A. P. Watt and Son
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
A. P. Watt & Son
A. P. Watt and Son is a British literary agency founded in 1875 by A. P. (Alexander Pollock) Watt. Under A. P. Watt and later his son Alec Watt, the firm served as literary agents for Rudyard Kipling from 1889 until Kipling's death in 1936.
Scope and Contents
The records include writings, correspondence and printed materials by or relating to Rudyard Kipling. Writings consist of holograph manuscripts, corrected typescripts, and corrected proofs. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters from Rudyard Kipling to A. P. Watt and Alec Watt written between 1889 and 1936 concerning both the publication of Kipling's writings and personal matters. Pamphlets by Kipling comprise the bulk of the printed material, which also includes clippings, ephemera and various other items.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Series I. Writings, 1891-1920s. Series II. Correspondence, 1889-1938. Series III. Printed materials, 1891-1945.
Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; Literary agents -- Great Britain; Literary agents -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936; Watt, Alec; Watt, A. P. (Alexander Pollock), 1834-1914; A. P. Watt and Son
- Writings, 1891-1920s; Series I
  Arrangement
  Writings are arranged in loose alphabetical order.
  - "The Ape One Dark Night" - manuscript, 1891 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - "Back to the Army Again" - manuscript (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Birds of Prey' March (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Edited typescript, signed by Rudyard Kipling.
  - The Bridge-Builders (Box 1)
    Edited proof.
  - Burials at Blauwkop (Box 1)
    Manuscript and typescript for the fourth page.
  - The Captive (Box 1)
    Edited typescript.
  - Cholera Camp (Box 1)
  - Cruisers, 2 (Box 1)
  - The Declaration of London (Box 1)
  - The Devil and the Deep Sea (Box 1)
  - A Diversity of Creatures, 3 (Box 1)
    Edited first proof, an edited second proof, and an edited third proof dealing with pages 1 through 272.
  - The Edge of the Evening (Box 1)
  - Egypt of the Magicians, 1914 April 2 (Box 1)
  - England and the War - preface, 1916 (Box 1)
  - The English Way (Box 1)
    Two typescripts.
  - The Feet of the Young Men, 2 (Box 1)
    Edited typescript and clean typescript.
  - The Female of the Species, 1911 (Box 1)
    Edited proof and clean proof.
  - "A Fleet in Being" - manuscript, 1898 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - For All We Have and Are, 1914 (Box 1)
  - "For to Admire" - manuscript, 1894 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - France at War (Box 1)
    Edited proofs.
  - Honours Even (Box 1)
  - Kim o' the Rishi (Box 1)
    Edited typescript of parts one, three and four.
  - Kipling facsimiles and printed note on sale of unauthorized editions (Box 1)
  - Kipling's Letters (Box 1)
  - Kipling's Poems (Box 1)
  - Letters of Travel, 1892-1913 (Box 1)
  - Lightenberg (Box 1)
  - The Liner She's a Lady (Box 1)
  - "Love o' Woman" - manuscript, 1893 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - The Mark of the Beast (Box 1)
  - Mary Postgate (Box 1)
  - Message for Empire Day (Box 1)
    Typescript, with an envelope to A. P. Watt.
  - The Miracles (Box 1)
  - "The Mother Dodge" - manuscript, 1895 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - The Mother Hive, 2 (Box 1)
  - Mrs. Bathurst (Box 1)
  - The New Army, 2 (Box 1)
  - The New Army in Training (Box 1)
  - "Original MSS., 'On Greenhow Hill' and Other Tales" - bound manuscript collection (Box 1)
  - Pan in Vermont - manuscript [collector's edition?], 1902 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Rebirth (Box 1)
    Typescript.
  - A Retired Gentleman (Box 1)
  - A Sahib's War (Box 1)
  - Sea Constables (Box 1)
  - Sea Warfare (Box 1)
  - The Ship That Found Herself (Box 1)
    Edited proof and an edited typescript.
  - Slaves of the Lamp (Box 1)
    Edited proof and a manuscript addition.
  - Songs from Books (Box 1)
  - The Son of His Father (Box 1)
  - "The Son of His Father" - manuscript, 1893 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - "The Song of Seven Cities" and "The Honours of War", 1911 (Box 1)
  - The Supports (Box 1)
    Clean typescript, signed by Rudyard Kipling.
  - The Tabu Tale (Box 1)
  - Tales of the Trade (Box 1)
    Edited typescript, dealing with parts 1 and 3.
  - That Day (Box 2)
  - Their Lawful Occasions (Box 2)
  - The Tomb of His Ancestors (Box 2)
  - "The Tomb of His Ancestors" - manuscript, 1897 (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - The Undertakers (Box 2)
  - An Unqualified Pilot (Box 2)
  - An Unrecorded Trial (Box 2)
  - With Number Three (Box 2)
    Manuscript signed.
  - The Vortex (Box 2)
  - The Years Between (Box 2)
    Typed notes.
  - "The Years Between" and "Dedication to the Seven Watchmen" (Box 2)
    Edited partial proof and an edited typescript.
- Correspondence, 1889-1938; Series II
  Correspondence is arranged in loose chronological order.
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Villiers St., Paternoster Sq., 1889; (3 letters) (Box 2)
  - Letter to Mr. Lang and St. Margaret's Church program and card, 1889-1924 (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Villiers St., London, circa 1890; (30 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Villiers St., Earls Court Rd, Dunedin, 1891; (10 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - London, Yokohawa, Montreal, Brattleboro, 1892; (18 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Brattleboro, 1893; (22 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Brattleboro, Tisbury, Gloucester, 1894; (23 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Brattleboro, Tisbury, Rottingdean, 1895; (22 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Warte, New York, Maidencombe, 1896; (33 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Burwash, London, Bermuda, 1897; (18 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Marychurch, Tisbury, 1897; (33 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Rottingdean, 1898; (14 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Rottingdean, Stourport, 1899; (4 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Norfolk St., London, Rottingdean, 1900; (5 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Rottingdean, Roseback, Burwash, 1901-1903; (12 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Bateman's Burwash, 1904-1912; (15 letters) (Box 2)
  - "The Female of the Species" photostat and letter re: "The Female," Flora Livingston to A. P. Watt, 1911-1928 (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - London, Bath, Tunbridge, 1914-1922; (11 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Brighton, Bateman's Burwash, 1923; (3 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Burwash, London, 1924; (4 letters) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence related to collection Rudyard Kipling editions, 1924-1938 (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Rue de Belles, Feuilles, 1926; (6 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Rio de Janero, 1927; (3 letters) (Box 2)
    Also includes photographs.
  - Livingston, Flora to A. P. Watt, 1927 December 24 (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Bateman's Burwash, Brooke St., 1928; (6 letters) (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard and Carrie Kipling to A. P. Watt - Tisbury, Paris, Bath, 1929; (5 letters) (Box 2)
    Includes four letters from Rudyard Kipling, and one letter from his wife, Carrie Balestier Kipling.
  - Watt, A. P. & Son, 1929-1931 (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard to A. P. Watt - Cannes, Burwash, Palace, 1932-1936; (12 letters and 1 postcard) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, clippings and lists relating to collecting and copyright (Box 5 (Oversize))
- Printed materials, 1891-1945; Series III
  Printed materials consist of works by Rudyard Kipling and others collected by A. P. Watt and Son.
  Printed materials are organized into three groups: pamphlets, clippings and ephemera, and other printed materials.
  - Pamphlets, 1891-1945
    Pamphlets are arranged in loose alphabetical order.
    - Address by Rudyard Kipling at the Annual Banquet of the France Grand Bretagne Assoc., 1931 July 2 (Box 2)
    - Address by Rudyard Kipling at the Annual Dinner of the Royal College of Surgeons, 1923 February 14 (Box 2)
    - Address by Rudyard Kipling at the Opening of the New Home at Milner Court, 1929 October 5 (Box 2)
    - Address by Rudyard Kipling at University College, 1923 October 12 (Box 2)
    - Annual Banquet Speeches, Chamber of Shipping of the United Kingdom, 1925 February 20 (Box 2)
      Also includes a table plan and guest list.
    - The Army of a Dream, 1904 (Box 2)
    - The Art of Fiction, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Author's Notes on the Names in the Jungle Books, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Beauty Spots, 1931 (Box 2)
    - B.E.L., 1944 (Box 2)
    - Below the Mill Dam, 1902 (Box 2)
    - Bonfires on the Ice, 1933 (Box 2)
    - Catalogue of Autograph Letters (Box 2)
    - Chartres Windows, 1925 (Box 2)
    - The Children's Song, 1914 (Box 2)
      Also includes a printed leaf.
    - A Choice of Songs, 1925 (Box 2)
    - A Choice of Songs, 1925; (2 copies) (Box 2)
    - The Church That Was at Antioch, 1929 (Box 2)
    - The City of Brass, 1909 (Box 2)
    - The City of Dreadful Night (Box 2)
    - College Echoes, St. Andrews University magazine, 1923 October 10 (Box 2)
    - Copyright in Letters (Box 2)
    - The Copyright Law of the United States of America, Library of Congress, 1936 (Box 2)
    - Correctanea, Being a Letter-Day Recording of Dinah Shadd, 1929 (Box 2)
    - The Covenanter, 1914 May 20 (Box 2)
    - The Conversion of St. Wilfred, 1909 (Box 2)
    - Cuckoo Song, 1909 (Box 2)
    - The Day of the Dead, 1930 (Box 2)
    - The Dead King, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Destroyers at Jutland, 1916 (Box 2)
      In four parts.
    - Doctors, The Waster, The Flight, Cain and Abel, The Appeal, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Eine Manöver-Flotte (Box 2)
    - England, speech for Royal Society of St. George, 1920 April 23 (Box 2)
    - "A Few Significant and Important KIPLING Items!" (Box 2)
    - A Fleet in Being, 1898; (2 copies) (Box 2)
    - The Fox Meditates, 1933 (Box 3)
    - France, 1913 (Box 3)
    - France at War, 1915 (Box 3)
    - France at War on the Frontier of Civilization, 1915 (Box 3)
      Parts 2 through 6.
    - The Fringes of the Fleet, 1915 (Box 3)
    - The Fringes of the Fleet, 1915 (Box 3)
      Consists of six parts.
    - The Fumes of the Heart, 1916 (Box 3)
    - Gloriana, 1909 (Box 3)
    - The Gods of the Copybook Headings, 1919 (Box 3)
    - Good Hunting, 1895 (Box 3)
    - Great-Heart, 1919 (Box 3)
    - The Great Play Hunt, 1930 (Box 3)
    - The Greek National Anthem, 1918 (Box 3)
    - Ham and the Porcupine, 1935 (Box 3)
    - Healing by the Stars, address to the Royal Society of Medicine, 1928 November 15 (Box 3)
    - His Apologies, 1932 (Box 3)
    - The Holy War, 1917; 2 (Box 3)
    - The Horse Marines, 1910 (Box 3)
    - Hymn of the Breaking Strain, 1935 (Box 3)
    - If—, 1914 (Box 3)
      Three trial copies and a small envelope.
    - Independence: Rectorial address at St. Andrews, 1923 October 10; 2 (Box 3)
    - The Irish Guards, 1918; 2 (Box 3)
    - The Islanders, 1902 (Box 3)
    - Justice, 1918 (Box 3)
    - The King's Pilgrimage (Box 3)
    - A Kipling Appendix, 1928 (Box 3)
    - Kipling on the Japanese, 1903 September 2 (Box 3)
    - The Last Rhyme of True Thomas, 1894 (Box 3)
    - Letters to the Family, 1908 (Box 3)
    - Letters to the Family, 1910 (Box 3)
    - The Light That Failed, 1891 (Box 3)
    - Liverpool Shipbroker's Benevolent Society, Inc.: Annual Report, 1928 (Box 3)
    - London Stone, 1923 (Box 3)
      Also includes two letters from the Copyright Office.
    - London Town, 1923 (Box 3)
    - Magdalene College magazine, 1932 July (Box 3)
    - The Manner of Men, 1930 (Box 3)
    - Mary Kingsley, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Mesopotamia, 1917 (Box 3)
    - Milner Court opening, 1929 October 7 (Box 3)
    - The Miracle of St. Jubanus, 1930 (Box 3)
    - A Nativity, 1917 (Box 3)
    - A Naval Mutiny, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Neighbors, 1932 (Box 3)
    - The Nerve That Conquers, 1928 (Box 3)
    - The Neutral, 1916 (Box 3)
    - The New Army, 1914 (Box 3)
      Includes parts 2 through 6.
    - The New Army in Training, 1915 (Box 3)
    - Our Lady of the Sackcloth, 1935 (Box 3)
    - "Pamphlet sheet... 1914" - empty folder (Box 3)
    - Pan in Vermont, 1902 (Box 3)
    - A Patrol Song, 1909 (Box 3)
    - A Pilgrim's Way, 1918 (Box 3)
    - The Pleasure Cruise, 1933 (Box 3)
    - The Private Account, 1916 (Box 3)
    - Proof Correction and House Style - J. M. Dent & Sons Ltd., 1945 (Box 3)
    - Proofs of Holy Writ, 1934 (Box 3)
    - The Question, 1916 (Box 3)
    - Railway Reform in Great Britain (Box 3)
    - A Rector's Memory, 1926 (Box 3)
    - Report of Speech at the Annual Dinner of the Chamber of Shipping of the UK, 1925 February 20; (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - A Retired Gentleman, 1916 (Box 3)
    - Rudyard Kipling with the British Fleet, 1915 (Box 3)
    - The Rhyme of Three Sealers, 1893 (Box 3)
    - Rudyard Kipling, 1899 (Box 3)
    - The Scholars, 1919 (Box 3)
    - Selected Poems, 1931 (Box 3)
    - Selections from The Freer Verse Horace, 1932 (Box 3)
    - The Shipping Industry, 1925 (Box 3)
    - Some Aspects of Travel, 1914 (Box 3)
    - Some Aspects of Travel: A Lecture before the Royal Geographical Society, 1914 (Box 3)
    - Something of Myself, 1938 (Box 3)
    - The Song of the Lathes, 1918 (Box 3)
    - Souvenirs of France, 1933 (Box 3)
      Includes two parts.
    - The Spies' March, 1911 (Box 3)
    - The Storm Come, 1932 (Box 3)
    - Supplication of the Black Aberdeen, 1927-1929; 3 (Box 3)
    - The Supports, 1919 (Box 3)
    - Tales of the Trade, 1916; 2 (Box 3)
    - "Teem"— A Treasure Hunter, 1935 (Box 3)
    - The Tender Achilles, 1929 (Box 3)
    - Three Poems, 1911 (Box 3)
    - Three Poems, 1934 (Box 3)
    - The Tree of Justice, 1909 (Box 3)
    - To the Companions, 1933 (Box 3)
    - Twenty Poems, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Unprofessional, 1930; (3 copies) (Box 4)
    - An Unrecorded Trail, 1913 (Box 4)
    - The War in the Mountain, 1917 (Box 4)
      Consists of five parts.
    - Wee Willie Winkle and Other Stories (Box 4)
    - The Wrong Thing, 1909 (Box 4)
    - Xmas, 1911 (Box 4)
  - Clippings and ephemera, 1906-1937
    - Bibliographies, typescripts of letters, newspaper clippings, 1906-1910 (Box 4)
    - Clippings and ephemera from Kipling Society and Kipling Memorial Fund, 1930s (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings and typed copies of letters, 1934-1937 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding Kipling (Box 4)
    - Photographs of Rudyard Kipling, (4 photographs) (Box 5 (Oversize))
      Includes two duplicates.
    - "Rudyard Kipling's New Book of Stories" - printed advertisement (Box 4)
    - "Scandal-Mongers" - clipping, typescripts, note from Watt to "Pon", 1927 September 23 (Box 4)
    - "Some of these, as 'Limited Editions,' may be valuable" - empty folder (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Other printed material, 1903-1937
    Arranged in loose alphabetical order.
    - Article in Fortune - "Doubleday, Doran & Co.", 1936 February (Box 4)
    - The Bookman: Rudyard Kipling Number - magazine, 1903 January (Box 4)
    - The Covenant - printed leaf, 1914 (Box 4)
    - The Declaration of London - printed leaf, 1911 (Box 4)
    - L'Envoi - published facsimile of draft (Box 4)
    - For All We Haven and Are - printed card, 1914 (Box 4)
    - The Holy War - printed sheet and proof with edits (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Hymn before Action - printed leaf (Box 4)
    - "M.I.: Mounted Infantry of the Line" - printed edition, 1931 (Box 5 (Oversize))
      Also includes illustrations and a letter.
    - "Order of Proceedings at the National Meeting" - program, 1932 January 27 (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - The Outlaws - printed leaves, 1914; 2 (Box 4)
    - Pan in Vermont - printed leaf, 1928; (3 copies) (Box 4)
    - Recessional - printed leaf and card (Box 4)
    - Twenty Poems - special limited edition, 1937 (Box 4)
    - Ulster - printed leaf, 1912 (Box 4)